Guide to the Martha Bradstreet Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Martha Bradstreet papers
1750-1877
1800-1840
GEN MSS 674
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(3 boxes, including 2 oversize boxes) + 23 broadside folders)
The papers consist chiefly of handwritten copies of maps, survey reports, and other legal documents related to litigation by Martha Bradstreet to gain title to land throughout the Mohawk River Valley in New York State. The land, including portions of Cosby's Manor and Utica, was originally the property of Major General John Bradstreet (1714-1774), the stepfather of her father, Samuel Bradstreet. The papers served as evidence for litigation by Martha Bradstreet against owners and tenants of the land. Survey reports and maps in the collection document landownership in the regions, as well as partitions and subdivisions made during the early nineteenth century within the Mohawk River Valley communities, especially in Utica, as well as Deerfield, Masonville, and Tompkins. The papers include a holograph manuscript of Bradstreet's An Offering at the Altar of Truth (1827). It details thirty-five cases she brought in federal courts and the unfavorable rulings made by Justice Alfred Conkling (1789-1874) of United States District Court for the Northern District of New York. A small amount of correspondence includes letters and draft letters pertaining to her litigation and personal letters from her friend Clarissa "Clara" Bartlett Gregory Catlin (1807-1845).
Bradstreet, Martha, 1780-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Martha Bradstreet (1780-1871)
Martha Bradstreet was born on the island of Antigua in the West Indies. Her father, Samuel Bradstreet (died 1784), named her after his sister, Martha Bradstreet (died 1782). She married Matthew Codd from Ireland in 1799 and divorced him in 1816. Their marriage produced five children, Elizabeth Catherine (later Bennett), Sarah Mary Anne (later Sterling), Eleanor Cloney, John Bradstreet, and Edward Livius (born circa 1809). Through acts in the New York State Assembly, she regained her birth name in 1817 and applied the surname of Bradstreet to her children in March 1818.
Martha Bradstreet inherited land in the Mohawk River Valley of New York through the estates of her father, her namesake, and aunts, Agatha Bradstreet Evans (died 1794) and Elizabeth Bradstreet Livius (died 1795). Most of the land originally accrued through the estates of her step-grandfather, Major General John Bradstreet (1714-1774) and her grandmother, Mary Aldridge Bradstreet (died 1782). However, poorly drafted deeds of sales created uncertain titles to a portion of the land. The terms of the estate of Elizabeth Bradstreet Livius further complicated Martha Bradstreet's land claims because she had married without the approval of the estate's executor. Bradstreet subsequently discovered that much of the land she inherited from her aunt Martha was sold by the estate's executor, Charles Gould (1726-1806) through his son and attorney, Edward Goold (Gould). During the early nineteenth century she pursued litigation to cancel the land sales and gain title to the properties designated for her in the bequests. In 1831, the United States Supreme Court denied her claim to portions land in Cosby's Manor, a tract of land in and around Utica, New York, in James Jackson, Ex Dem. of Martha Bradstreet, v. Henry Huntington, 30 U.S. 5 Pet. 402 (1831).
Bradstreet continued to pursue her land claims in communities throughout the Mohawk River Valley until her death in Bennettsville, New York.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist chiefly of handwritten copies of maps, survey reports, and other legal documents related to litigation by Martha Bradstreet to gain title to land throughout the Mohawk River Valley in New York State. The land, including portions of Cosby's Manor and Utica, was originally the property of Major General John Bradstreet (1714-1774), the stepfather of her father, Samuel Bradstreet. The papers served as evidence for litigation by Martha Bradstreet against owners and tenants of the land. Survey reports and maps in the collection document landownership in the regions, as well as partitions and subdivisions made during the early nineteenth century within the Mohawk River Valley communities, especially in Utica, as well as Deerfield, Masonville, and Tompkins. The papers include a holograph manuscript of Bradstreet's An Offering at the Altar of Truth (1827). It details thirty-five cases she brought in federal courts and the unfavorable rulings made by Justice Alfred Conkling (1789-1874) of United States District Court for the Northern District of New York. A small amount of correspondence includes letters and draft letters pertaining to her litigation and personal letters from her friend Clarissa "Clara" Bartlett Gregory Catlin (1807-1845).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series I. Maps, Legal Documents, and Writings, circa 1750-1877. Series II. Correspondence, 1837-1854. Each series is arranged chronologically in this guide, while materials are physically arranged by size and then chronologically.
Real property -- New York (State) -- New York; Deerfield (N.Y.: Town); Masonville (N.Y.); Mohawk River Valley (N.Y.); Tompkins (N.Y.); Utica (N.Y.); Legal documents; Maps (documents); Bradstreet family; Bradstreet, John, 1711-1774 -- Estate; Bradstreet, Martha, 1780-; Bradstreet, Martha, 1780- -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Bradstreet, Samuel, -1784; Catlin, Clarissa Bartlett Gregory, 1807-1845; Conkling, Alfred, 1789-1874
- Maps, Legal Documents, and Writings, circa 1750-1877; Series I; 87
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically in this finding aid, materials are physically arranged by size and then chronologically..
  - Map of land owned by John Bradstreet and D. Campbell in the Springfield Patent, north of Otsego Lake, New York, circa 1750 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Extract regarding three tracts of land at Deepy Kill, near Lansingburgh, New York, 1772 July 4; copied 1868 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Patents, survey reports, and division of land between the Susquehanna River and Delaware River, New York, granted to heirs of John Bradstreet, 1786 January 12-1787 May 15; copied 1848 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Map of land between the Susquehanna River and Delaware River, New York, granted to the heirs of John Bradstreet, circa 1786 (Box 2, Folder 48A-48B)
  - Survey reports and division of land between the Susquehanna River and Delaware River, New York, granted to heirs of John Bradstreet, 1787 May 15; copied 1810 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Statement by Jebediah Sawyer of monies paid to Charles John Evans and Edward Goold from lands sold in Cosby's Manor, New York, 1790 November 19-1798 November 23 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Lists of deeds executed by Edward Goold and others for lands in Cosby's Manor, New York, 1790 December 24-1807 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Memorandum designating Samuel Preston to protect and sell land for Charles John Evans, Samuel Ludlow, and Edward Goold, 1791 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Patent Granted to the Heirs of the Late General Bradstreet, 1792 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Printed broadside signed by Charles John Evans and Edward Goold that advertises land for sale through their representative, Samuel Preston.
  - Survey and map of the division of a gore of land between the Delaware River and Susquehanna River by William Cockburn, 1792 October 10-1793 April 20
    - Original, 1792 October 10 (Box 2, Folder 51A)
    - Copy 1, copied 1818 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 51B)
    - Copy 2, copied 1848 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Maps for tracts of land in Lot No. 97 in Cosby's Manor described in a deed by Philip John Schuyler (1733-1804) as executor of the last will and testament of John Bradstreet, 1794 May 16; copied 1840 February 3; 2 maps (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Description of the division of a gore of land between the Delaware River and Susquehanna River by land commissioners Daniel McCormick and Richard Harrison, 1795 January 10 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Receipt from Edward Goold to Samuel Preston that documents the sale of Lot No. 44 to John Hulse, 1795 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Map of lots on Whitesborough Street in Utica, New York, surveyed by Calvin Guiteau for Adam G. Mappa, 1800 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Map of lots on Whitesborough Street, Genesee Street, Hotel Street, and Seneca Street in Utica, New York, surveyed by Calvin Guiteau for Adam G. Mappa, 1800 October (Box Bsd, folder 70)
  - Diagram of the estate of John Bradstreet as divided by him and his daughter, Martha Bradstreet (died 1782), circa 1800 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Map of portions of Lot Nos. 94 and 95 in Cosby's Manor, New York, purchased by John Post on October 22, 1804, and surveyed by Werden Hammond, 1804 November (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Diagram of lots surveyed and subdivided by Charles C. Brodhead in Frankfort, New York, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Map of subdivisions in Lots Nos. 57, 58, 59, 60, and 61 in Cosby's Manor, New York, by land commissioners; map created by Charles C. Brodhead, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Map of subdivisions and land ownership in Lot No. 79, in Cosby's Manor, New York; map created by Charles C. Brodhead, circa 1805 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Map of subdivisions in Lot No. 79 of Cosby's Manor, New York; map created by Charles C. Brodhead, 1805, copied 1819 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Map of subdivisions in Lot Nos. 99 and 100 in Utica, New York, circa 1805 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Account of Matthew Codd with Hugh Cunningham, 1806 November 19-1809 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Map of portions of Lot No. 97 of Cosby's Manor in Utica, New York, owned by Henry Huntington and William F. Potter, 1807; 2 maps (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Map of the Post Lot in Utica, New York, surveyed by Charles C. Brodhead
    - Copy 1, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Copy 2, larger, 1808 (Box Bsd, folder 71)
  - Letter by attorney John Vernor Henry (1767-1829) to the executors of the estate of Philip John Schuyler (1733-1804) outlining his opinion about the ownership of a gore of land in Cosby's Manor, New York, 1810 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Diagram of subdivision lots in Lot No. 13 of the Evans Patent in Masonville, New York, circa 1810 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Map of Lot No. 95 of Cosby's Manor, Utica, New York, circa 1810 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Map of the Post Purchase Lot in Utica, New York, surveyed by Charles C. Brodhead, 1812 November (Box Bsd, folder 72)
  - Map of the Hotel Lot between Water Street and Whitesborough Street, Utica, New York, surveyed by Calvin Guiteau, 1813 June, copied circa 1819 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Map of the Hotel Lot between the Mohawk River and Water Street, Utica, New York, surveyed by Calvin Guiteau, 1813 June (Box Bsd, folder 73)
  - Map of Lots Nos. 73, 74, 75, and 76 between Seneca Street and Genesee Street in Utica, New York, subdivided by Charles C. Brodhead, 1814 January 16 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Map of Lot No. 3 in Cosby's Manor, Deerfield, New York, surveyed by Calvin Guiteau, 1815 October (Box Bsd, folder 74)
  - Map of part of Alexander Cockburn's Gore in Masonville, New York, surveyed by Jonathan Kernsted, 1815 (Box Bsd, folder 75)
  - Map of the subdivisions in Lot No. 3 in Deerfield, New York, surveyed by Calvin Guiteau and divided by Apollos Cooper, A. Coventry, and Calvin Guiteau, circa 1815 (Box Bsd, folder 76)
  - Map of the new location of Block No. 25 and Lot Nos. 39, 40, 41, 42, and 43 in the Post Purchase Lot, Utica, New York, surveyed by Charles C. Brodhead, 1816 June (Box Bsd, folder 77)
  - Map of the Post Purchase Lot in Utica, New York, surveyed by Charles C. Brodhead in 1812 and altered in 1815, 1816 August 22 (Box Bsd, folder 78)
  - Map of the Post Purchase Lot in Utica, New York, surveyed by Charles C. Brodhead in 1812 and altered in 1815, 1816 August 22 (Box Bsd, folder 79)
  - Map of subdivisions in Lot No. 2 in Cosby's Manor, New York, subdivided by Charles C. Brodhead, 1819 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Map of subdivisions in Lot No. 47 in Cosby's Manor, New York, subdivided by Charles C. Brodhead, 1819 April 8 (Box Bsd, folder 80)
  - Survey book and maps for Lot Nos. 67 and 71 of the Evans Patent surveyed by Sluman Bartlett, which includes Tompkins, New York, 1820 August (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Accompanied by a sale order and receipt for the book and maps
  - Map of the northeast part of Lot No. 96 in Cosby's Manor and Utica, New York, owned by James S. Kip, circa 1820 July (Box Bsd, folder 81)
    On the verso is a map of property conveyed by James S. Kip to Davis P. Hoyt on July 28, 1820
  - Map of the Evans Patent and Gore, New York, circa 1820 (Box 2, Folder 61A)
    Lands claimed by Martha Bradstreet filled in yellow and land of the Walton Lower Patent filled in blue.
  - Map of land in Lot Nos. 89 and 90 in Cosby's Manor, New York, conveyed by Abigail E. Butler Wolcott, widow of Dr. Solomon Wolcott (1769-1818), surveyed by Selig Gifford, 1821 April 24 (Box Bsd, folder 82)
  - Survey book and maps for division of Lot Nos. 4, 8, 20, 24 and 30 of the Evans Patent in Tompkins New York, surveyed by Sluman Bartlett, 1821 September (Box 2, Folder 61B)
  - Diagram of subdivisions in Lot No. 13 of the Evans Patent in Masonville, New York, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Map of Post Purchase Lot in Utica, New York, created by H. Hutchinson, 1824 (Box Bsd, folder 83)
  - Map of Broadway, Washington Street, and Genesee Street in the Post Purchase Lot in Utica, New York, circa 1824 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Map of Hopper Street, Court Street, and Genesee Street in the Post Purchase Lot in Utica, New York, circa 1824 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Maps of subdivisions in Lot Nos. 4, 8, 13, 20, 24, 30, 37, 40, 44, 50, 58, and 62 in the Evans Patent, New York, circa 1825 (Box 1, Folder 19-30)
  - Map of lots owned by William Tillman between Genesee Street, Hotel Street, and Liberty Street in Utica, New York, 1825 August 25 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Map of subdivisions in Lot Nos. 67 and 68 in Utica, New York, made for William Williams by William Jones, 1827 May (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Map of subdivisions between Broadway, Lafayette Street, and Canal (Court) Street in Utica, New York, made for James S. Kip by William Jones, 1827 May (Box Bsd, folder 84)
  - Manuscript of An Offering at the Altar of Truth, circa 1827 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Copyright deposit for An Offering at the Altar of Truth, 1827 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Diagram illustration the compensation claim of Henry White and John Williams following the enlargement of the Erie Canal on Charlotte Street in Utica, New York, circa 1827 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Map in the vicinity of Steuben Park in Utica, New York, made for A. Seymour by John Fish, 1829 February (Box Bsd, folder 85)
  - Letter of Attorney from Ann Mason that designates Wearam Willis (1780-1860) to act on her behalf, 1830 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Map of subdivisions in the vicinity of Hopper Street and Genesee Street, Utica, New York, owned by Maria Miller and subdivided by William Jones in July 1826, circa 1830 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Map of land owned by William Butler on Charlotte Street between Steuben Park and Blandina Street, Utica, New York, 1833 April 29 (Box Bsd, folder 86)
  - Map of land in Lot Nos. 89 and 90 in Cosby's Manor, New York, conveyed by Abigail E. Butler Wolcott, widow of Dr. Solomon Wolcott (1769-1818) and subdivided by ensuing owners, 1835 (Box Bsd, folder 87)
  - Map of land owned by Apollos Cooper (1767-1839) in the vicinity of Mandeville Street, Cornelia Street, and Aikin Street in Utica, New York, 1836 January 1 (Box Bsd, folder 88)
  - Map of land owned by A. Williams in the vicinity of Louisa Street, Leah Street, and Steuben Street in Utica, New York, 1836 January 9 (Box Bsd, folder 89)
  - Map of Lots in the Fourth Ward of Utica, printed by C. B. Graham's Lithography, New York, circa 1837 (Box Bsd, folder 90)
  - Map of lands owned by the heirs of John M. Mason and Anna Mason in Evans Patent in Masonville, New York, 1838 October 9 (Box Bsd, folder 91)
    Accompanied by an attached report by land commissioners charged by a chancery to partition the estate.
  - Map of Lot No. 43 in Cosby's Manor, New York, which shows land conveyed by Martha Bradstreet to the Utica & Schenectady Rail Road Company, circa 1840 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Map of Lot Nos. 42, 43, and 44 in Cosby's Manor, New York, circa 1840 (Box Bsd, folder 92)
  - Map and notes related to the Gore of Cosby's Manor, New York, 1843 July (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Outline map of the Gore of Cosby's Manor, New York, circa 1843 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Transcript of proceedings of the Canal Appraisers of the State of New York and award to Charles Gray for damages caused by enlarging the Erie Canal in Frankfort, New York, 1845 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Portion of printed map that shows land patents in Delaware County, New York, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Diagram of the subdivision of Lot No. 91 of Cosby's Manor in Bainbridge, New York, by E. P. Bennett, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Memoranda of facts related to Martha Bradstreet v. Charles Gray, 1863 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Sketch of Lot No. 44 in the Evans Patent, New York, by Marshal Hulce for Edward Livius Bradstreet, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Outline map of an irregularly shaped land lot, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Correspondence, 1837-1854; Series II; 5
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Clarissa "Clara" Bartlett Gregory Catlin (1807-1845) to Martha Bradstreet, 1837 February 8-June 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Three letters that document their friendship as well as debts that she and her husband, American painter and author George Catlin (1796-1872), owe Bradstreet, and vice versa. A letter mentions portraits Catlin offered Lewis Beck, professor of geology at Rutgers University. A promissory note for five dollars from Bradstreet to George Catlin accompanies the letters.
  - Martha Bradstreet to "Sir", circa 1838 January (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Documents her journey from Albany, New York, to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
  - Martha Bradstreet to Canal Appraisers of the State of New York, 1842 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    A draft letter that details her claim for damages incurred to her property by the Erie Canal in Frankfort, New York
  - Martha Bradstreet to stock holders, 1847 July (Box 1, Folder 44)
    A draft letter that details her property claims to stockholders of an unidentified construction project on Lot No. 90 of Cosby's Manor, New York
  - Martha Bradstreet to Henry Augustus Muhlenberg (1823-1854), 1854 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Details her continuing litigation and news of shared acquaintances. Muhlenberg died on January 9, 1854, so Bradstreet consequently did not send the letter.